<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33708306</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7906545</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-34-137</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2019.34.137.14902</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Primary adenoid cystic carcinoma of the tracheobronchial tree: report of two cases</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>Ahmed Ben</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x00026;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kadoussi</surname><given-names>Rania</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Njima</surname><given-names>Manel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mhamed</surname><given-names>Saousen Cheikh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fahem</surname><given-names>Nesrine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdeljelil</surname><given-names>Nouha Ben</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joobeur</surname><given-names>Samah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rouatbi</surname><given-names>Naceur</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Pulmonology Department, Fattouma Bourguiba Hospital, Monastir, Tunisia</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Fattouma Bourguiba Hospital, Monastir, Tunisia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x00026;</label>Corresponding author: Ahmed Ben Saad, Pulmonology Department, Fattouma Bourguiba Hospital, Monastir, Tunisia</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><elocation-id>137</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Ahmed Ben Saad et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Adenoid cystic carcinoma (ACC) is a rare malignant epithelial tumor that predominantly originates in the salivary glands. Primary ACC of the tracheobronchial tree is extremely rare. We report two new cases of central airways primary ACC: a 58 year-old male with an ACC of the left main bronchus who underwent a pneumonectomy with node dissection, and a 52 year-old female with proximal tracheal ACC presenting as asthma treated by surgical resection and a postoperative radiotherapy. Primary ACC of the tracheobronchial tree is often misdiagnosed given the non-specific clinical presentation. An early diagnosis is essential to ensure good outcomes. An interdisciplinary treatment is required based especially on surgery and radiotherapy.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Adenoid cystic carcinoma</kwd><kwd>salivary gland cancer</kwd><kwd>lung cancer</kwd><kwd>bronchogenic carcinoma</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Adenoid cystic carcinoma (ACC) is a malignant tumor that originate mainly from the salivary glands. The pulmonary localization is rare accounting for 0.04 to 0.2% [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is generally located in the proximal tracheobronchial tree. The involvement of the pulmonary parenchyma is exceptional. Primary pulmonary ACC has no specific clinical or imaging features. The diagnosis is confirmed by histopathology. The evolution is generally favorable provided an early diagnosis and a complete surgical resection [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Patient and observation</title><p><bold>Case 1</bold>: a 58 year- old male with 80 pack-years of cigarettes was hospitalized in our department for the exploration of hemoptysis with cough and sputum, initially diagnosed as pneumonia. There is no history of tuberculosis. Chest auscultation revealed ronchi in left basal region. Complete blood count and blood biochemistry were within normal limits. Sputum was negative for acid fast bacilli or other pathogenic germs. His chest X-ray showed a persistent left basal consolidation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>). Thoracic CT scan revealed a left-sided bronchialcentric mass in the left main bronchus associated with multiple left hilar lymph nodes and carcinomatous lymphangitis in the left inferior lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>). Cerebral and abdomino-pelvic CT scan did not reveal metastatic lesions. Bronchial fibroscopy showed an endobronchial polypoidal growth in the left main bronchus that entirely occlude the lumen. The histopathological examination of bronchial biopsy showed evidence of adenoid cystic carcinoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>). The patient underwent a left pneumonectomy with node dissection. The surgical margins were negative with no node dissemination. A Chest CT performed seven months following surgery didn&#x02019;t show tumor recurrence. The patient is regularly seen at our consultation. He reports an improvement of his symptoms after the surgery.</p><fig id="f0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Chest X ray-case 1: persistent left basal consolidation (white star) with a left mediastinal attraction (white arrow)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-34-137-g001"/></fig><fig id="f0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Chest CT scan-case 1: (A) axial CT scan image; (B) coronal CT scan image. Left-sided bronchial-centric mass in the left main bronchus (white arrow) associated with multiple left hilar lymph nodes and carcinomatous lymphangitis in the left inferior lobe</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-34-137-g002"/></fig><fig id="f0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Histopathology: (A) adenoid cystic carcinoma showing cribriform and tubular growth of small hyperchromatic epithelial cells (yellow arrow) (HEx40); (B) tumoral cells are cuboidal with scant cytoplasm and homogenous nuclei (yellow arrow) (HEx400)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-34-137-g003"/></fig><p><bold>Case 2</bold>: we report the case of a 52 year-old female with insulin-dependent diabetes who was followed as outpatient during four years for cough, wheezing and dyspnea with progressive worsening. The diagnosis of non-allergic asthma was initially suspected and the patient was treated with a long-acting &#x003b2;2 agonist treatment in association with an inhaled corticosteroid. Despite the regular use of an optimal treatment, her symptoms were worsening. Chest X ray showed a mediastinal widening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4</xref>). Spirometry showed a flattened inspiratory curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref>). The thoracic CT scan revealed a proximal tracheal solid mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6</xref>). So a Surgical resection of fours tracheal rings was performed. The histopathological analysis concluded to the diagnosis of adenoid cystic carcinoma with positive surgical margins. The patient received postoperative radiotherapy. She had a postoperative follow up of six months with a clear improvement in dyspnea.</p><fig id="f0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Chest X ray - case 2: mediastinal widening (white arrow)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-34-137-g004"/></fig><fig id="f0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Spirometry: flow volume loop: flattened inspiratory curve (black arrow)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-34-137-g005"/></fig><fig id="f0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Chest CT scan - case 2: (A) axial CT scan image; (B) coronal CT scan image. Proximal tracheal solid mass (yellow arrow)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-34-137-g006"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Adenoid cystic carcinomas (or cylindroma) are malignant epithelial tumors that have a slow development. It occurs mainly in the salivary glands, but can also affect other sites such as lungs, breasts, skin and uterine cervix [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It represents 20 to 35% of tracheal tumors [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Primary adenoid cystic carcinoma in the lungs mostly affects the main airway like the trachea or main bronchi. Pulmonary parenchyma involvement is extremely rare [<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. It affects both sexes similarly and especially young one aged between 4 th and 5 th decades [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Our two patients belong to this interval. There is no evidence of association with tobacco smoking. Clinical manifestations are not specific, dominated mainly by hemoptysis and dyspnea as it was for our patients [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Our second case illustrate the example of ACC presenting as asthma. In some cases, the tumor can be asymptomatic resulting in a delayed diagnosis. The histopathological diagnosis is based mainly on the bronchoscopy since the proximal endoluminal growth of the tumor, allowing the realization of a biopsy or a bronchoscope-guided fine-needle aspiration [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Hematoxylin-eosin staining remains the principal method used for the diagnosis of ACC.</p><p>Immunohistochemistry can be useful in some case. Indeed there is three types of growth to be distinguished on histology: cribriform, tubular and solid. There is a correlation between the evolution of ACC and the histological models. The solid pattern is the most aggressive compared to cribriform [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] .For our patients, the first case was a tubular and cribriform ACC whereas it was of solid type for the second case. The treatment is essentially based on surgical resection for early stage. Postoperative radiotherapy is indicated in the case of positive surgical margins and for non-operable patients [<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Indeed, ACC is characterized by a possible submucosally and perineurally spread. The place of chemotherapy remains a controversial subject. There is some cases described in the literature that had a response to chemotherapy especially in metastatic cases. The prognosis of ACC depends on histological growth patterns, stage and margins of surgical resection. ACC has a good prognosis with a low metastatic risk especially in patients undergoing radical surgical treatment with clear margins [<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Otherwise, recurrence or metastases may occur [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Thus, a prolonged period of follow up is needed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>ACC is a tumor of good prognosis provided an early diagnosis and rapid management based essentially on surgical resection associated in some cases with radiotherapy. It has no specific clinical presentation leading often to a late diagnosis. More studies are needed to determine the contribution of chemotherapy especially in metastatic tumors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>All authors participated in the preparation of the manuscript. Naceur Rouatbi and Samah Joobeur conceptualised and designed the manuscript. Ahmed Ben Saad and Rania Kadoussi performed manuscript writing. Manel Njima and Nouha Ben Abdeljelil performed the histopathologic examination. Saousen Cheikh Mhamed and Nesrine Fahem revised the english version. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chhabra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhutani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary adenoid cystic carcinoma of bronchus: Report of a rare case</article-title><source>Human Pathology</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraire</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dail</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tracheobronchial Tumors of the Salivary Gland Type</article-title><source>Dail and Hammar's Pulmonary Pathology: Volume II: Neoplastic Lung Disease</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>426</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dattachaudhuri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhanja</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rare case of primary adenoid cystic carcinoma of lung</article-title><source>Indian J Chest Dis Allied Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25823114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwashita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanegae</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujinaga</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peripheral pulmonary adenoid cystic carcinoma with substantial submucosal extension to the proximal bronchus</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1991</year><month>2</month><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1849668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>zaibi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>ben amar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Frikha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Le carcinome ad&#x000e9;noide kystique primitif, une tumeur bronchique rare</article-title><source>La tunisie m&#x000e9;dicale</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>698</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28994876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nampoothiri</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaharopoulos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Logrono</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary pulmonary adenoid cystic carcinoma: report of a case diagnosed by fine-needle aspiration cytology</article-title><source>Diagn Cytopathol</source><year>2004</year><month>1</month><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14696146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ratto</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Alloisio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiaramondia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary peripheral adenoid cystic carcinoma of the lung. A case report</article-title><source>Acta Chir Belg</source><year>2003</year><month>8</month><volume>103</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14524164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousem</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller-Hermelink</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adenoid cystic carcinoma</article-title><source>Pathology and Genetics of Tumours of the Lung, Pleura, Thymus and Heart</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Lyon, France</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IARC Press</publisher-name><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary adenoid cystic carcinoma of the lung: Clinicopathological features, treatment and results</article-title><source>Oncol Lett</source><year>2015</year><month>3</month><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1475</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25663934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iype</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankar</surname><given-names>UV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adenoid Cystic Carcinoma of the Trachea</article-title><source>Indian J Surg Oncol</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27065684</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>