<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Orthop Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Orthop Case Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Orthopaedic Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2250-0685</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2321-3817</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Indian Orthopaedic Research Group</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32548036</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7276600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JOCR-9-82</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13107/jocr.2019.v09.i06.1600</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rare Presentation of Benign Osteochondroma: A Case Report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ratra</surname><given-names>Rohan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peshin</surname><given-names>Chetan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Orthopedics, Himalayan Institute of Medical Sciences, Swami Rama Himalayan University, Jolly Grant, Dehradun, Uttarakhand, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address of Correspondence:</bold> Dr. Rohan Ratra, Department of Orthopedics, Himalayan Institute of Medical Sciences, Swami Rama Himalayan University, Jolly Grant, Dehradun, Uttarakhand, India. <bold>E-mail:</bold><email xlink:href="rohanratra@gmail.com">rohanratra@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Indian Orthopaedic Research Group</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Osteochondromas are the most common benign bone tumors (accounting for 20&#x02013;50% of all benign bone tumors). They are developmental malformations rather than true neoplasms and are thought to originate within the periosteum. They usually affect bones that develop by enchondral ossification and rarely originate from bones that develop by intramembranous ossification such as the scapula, pubic rami, clavicle, and ribs.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Case Report</title><p>We present a case of a 24-year-old male, who came with a swelling in the right side inguinal region for 2 years which was diagnosed to be osteochondroma by trocar biopsy. The site and presentation are rare. The patient had no visceral or vascular involvement though the lesion was very near many vital structures on superior pubic ramus.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Osteochondroma arising from the pelvis is an unusual presentation which should be kept in mind as a differential diagnosis when evaluating mass in pelvis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Osteochondroma</kwd><kwd>exostosis</kwd><kwd>pubic ramus</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text position="float"><caption><title>Learning Point of the Article:</title></caption><p>Pelvic osteochondroma is indeed a rare presentation and should be kept in mind while evaluating a pelvic mass.</p></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Osteochondromas are the most common benign bone tumors (accounting for 20&#x02013;50% of all benign bone tumors). They are developmental malformations rather than true neoplasms and are thought to originate within the periosteum [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Inheritance pattern is autosomal dominant which can cause multiple exostoses or isolated lesion [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. They usually present during the period of rapid skeletal growth and cease to grow once maturity is reached [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The patient usually complaints of swelling and cosmetic deformity [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. They can present either as a pedunculated or a sessile mass (latter being more common)[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The lesion is typically mushroom-shaped affecting metaphysis of long bones such as femur and tibia [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. It usually affects bones that develop by enchondral ossification and rarely originates from bones that develop by intramembranous ossification such as the scapula, pubic ramus, clavicle, and ribs [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. We report a rare case of pedunculated variety of osteochondroma developing at an unusual site &#x02013;superior pubic ramus.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases" id="sec1-2"><title>Case Report</title><p>A 24-year-old healthy male student presented with complaints of a swelling in the right side inguinal region for 2 years. The swelling was insidious in onset, gradually progressive and was not associated with pain, but the patient complained of irritation and mass effect due to the swelling specially when wearing belt or tight clothing. On examination, there was a hard swelling of approximately 8 cm &#x000d7; 11cm size over the right inguinal region, medial to the mid-inguinal point. The swelling was non-tender, non-mobile, and fixed to underlying bone but not adherent to skin or overlying tissue. Cough impulse was absent.</p><p>X-ray pelvis with both hips anteroposterior view and oblique views (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) showed exostosis arising from superior pubic rami. Non-contrast helical computerized tomography (CT)pelvis with both hips (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) showed a pedunculated round to oval lesion in continuity with cortex of superior pubic rami on the right side arising from outside surface. It had a cartilaginous cap. It measured 8 cm &#x000d7; 4.6 cm &#x000d7; 5cm in size. CT scan of pelvis confirmed the bony nature of swelling.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Radiograph at presentation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOCR-9-82-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Radiograph at presentation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOCR-9-82-g002"/></fig><p>Trocar biopsy was taken first under C-arm guidance. Histopathological examination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) showed bony trabeculae along with cartilage with no evidence of dysplasia. Excisional biopsy of the tumor from the right superior pubic rami was performed using ilioinguinal approach. Intraoperatively, we noticed that tumor was in the plane between superficial abdominal wall and pubic ramus, and no need to open inguinal canal was felt. It was carefully operated using blunt and sharp dissection and excised from stalk. There was no infiltration into surrounding structure and tumor came out in toto. Macroscopically, it measured 90 cm &#x000d7; 60 cm &#x000d7; 20cm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Outer surface had bosselated grayish-white appearance. The tumor involved midpart of superior pubic ramus with cap of mature cartilage covering the bone.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Radiograph post-operative.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOCR-9-82-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Non-contrast helical computerized tomography scan.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOCR-9-82-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Gross specimen.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOCR-9-82-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>(a and b) Histopathological specimen showing bony trabeculae with bone intertrabecular tissue. The bone is covered by a cap of mature cartilage.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JOCR-9-82-g006"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The overall incidence of osteochondroma reported in literature is 35% of benign and 8% of all bone tumors [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Osteochondromas usually develop in bones that develop by enchondral ossification and rarely develop in bones developing by intramembranous ossification like pelvis [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Among the long bones, the most common site affected is distal femur [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Male predominance is seen with the ratio of 1.6&#x02013;3.4:1 [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].Osteochondromas are usually seen in growing age group as they develop as cartilaginous overgrowth from physeal plate [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. They have been reported to develop due to hematopoietic stem cell transplantation and due to surgery/radiation-induced injury [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Genetic etiology of the disease is well established with tumor suppressor gene EXT1 and EXT2 being the culprit for the disease [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>A thorough search of literature was made to find out the rarity of the case. PubMed and Google Scholar database were used to find out articles reporting osteochondroma arising from pubic rami. According to Rizzoli institution statistical data, only seven cases of osteochondroma arising from pubic rami were reported worldwide until 2009 [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Recently, Nekkanti et al. reported a case of sessile osteochondroma arising from iliac wing [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. A cadaveric case report of osteochondroma arising from pubis was given by Nayak et al., in 2018 [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Osteochondromas cause symptoms only when they become large enough to cause a mass effect and compression of nearby structures. Review of recent literature shows that compression of lumbosacral nerve roots is common with pelvic osteochondromas [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Location of the tumor can be judged according to the symptoms of nerve compression. An iliac mass would cause lumbar nerve root compression, whereas an ischial mass would put pressure on sciatic nerves [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Urogenital structures can also be compressed by a large osteochondroma. The patient can have symptoms of bladder outlet obstruction due to compression of bladder neck and urethra [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Osteochondroma is a benign neoplasm but has the potential of malignant transformation. About 1% incidence of chondrosarcoma developing from osteochondroma has been reported in literature [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. One case of chondrosarcoma development form pelvic osteochondroma has been published in the past [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Development of chondrosarcoma or neurovascular compromise is an absolute indication for tumor excision [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Our patient had no symptoms of any organ compression and complained only of a swelling in the right side pubic region causing irritation and pain on walking and squatting. We noticed that the tumor mass was present on ventral surface of the right superior pubic ramus. It was away from the hip joint, femoral neurovascular bundle and pubic viscera. The tumor was, therefore, excised enbloc. Ilioinguinal approach was used for the excision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>We report this case due to its unusual site of presentation. These tumors are usually asymptomatic but can cause pubic viscera compression or neurovascular compromise. These are usually operated due to cosmetic reasons with a very low incidence of recurrence. Pelvic osteochondromas should be kept in mind as differential of a bony hard pelvic mass.</p><boxed-text position="float"><caption><title>Clinical Message</title></caption><p>Certain tumors present unusually at rare sites which make the diagnosis challenging for the surgeon. Although rare, osteochondroma can present in bones developing by intramembranous ossification. Detailed evaluation becomes necessary.</p></boxed-text></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> Nil</p></fn><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Consent:</bold> The authors confirm that Informed consent of the patient is taken for publication of this case report</p></fn></fn-group><bio id="d36e314"><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="JOCR-9-82-g007.gif"/></p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="JOCR-9-82-g008.gif"/></p></bio><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>KR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Canale</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaty</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benign bone tumors and neoplastic conditions simulating bone tumors</article-title><source>Campbell's Operative Orthopaedics</source><year>2007</year><edition>11th ed</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mobsy Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>858</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oljaca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirzberger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergovec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiesenhausen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koter</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesenbichler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Osteochondroma of the scapula associated with a subclavian artery pseudoaneurysm:Case report</article-title><source>SAGE Open Med Case Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2050313X18823089</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taheriazam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeidinia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One-stage surgical excision of a huge bilateral multiple osteochondroma of the hip:A case report</article-title><source>Electron Physician</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5310</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29038715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nekkanti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Savsani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Meka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahtani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rare sessile variant of osteochondroma presenting at an unusual site of the iliac wing in a 15-year old boy</article-title><source>J Orthop Allied Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buch</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Castelino</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rare clinical presentation of an osteochondroma of coronoid process of mandible</article-title><source>J Dent Shiraz Univ Med Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f6;kku&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Atmaca</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sa&#x0011f;ta&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Saylik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteochondromas originating from unusual locations complicating orthopedic discipline:Case series</article-title><source>EklemHastalikCerrahisi</source><year>2015</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bovee</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilpshaar</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bone:Osteochondroma</article-title><source>Atlas Genet Cytogenet Oncol Haematol</source><year>2019</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalsotra</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solitary osteochondroma of the ilium:A case report</article-title><source>Int J Orthop Surg</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1 4</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herode</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandlewala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rare case of pubic ramus osteochondroma</article-title><source>J Orthop Case Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27299069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirasanagandla</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivas</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pamidi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Solitary osteochondroma in the body of the pubic bone:A cadaveric case report</article-title><source>Anat Cell Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29984059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bangroo</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanda</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Maqsood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolated osteochondroma of the ilium:Case report with review of the literature.Scholars J Appl Med Sci</article-title><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1573</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solitary pelvic osteochondroma causing L5 nerve root compression</article-title><source>Orthopedics</source><year>2009</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>922</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19968229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Osteochondroma of the symphysis pubis:A rare cause of bladder outlet obstruction</article-title><source>Am Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20726435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nystrom</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeYoung</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morcuende</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Secondary chondrosarcoma of the pelvis arising from a solitary exostosis in an 11-year-old patient:A case report with 5-year follow-up</article-title><source>Iowa Orthop J</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24027486</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>