<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vasc Surg Cases Innov Tech</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Vasc Surg Cases Innov Tech</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Vascular Surgery Cases and Innovative Techniques</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2468-4287</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30911703</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6416376</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2468-4287(18)30136-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvscit.2018.10.008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Vascular infection</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Open surgical ligation of a symptomatic mycotic aneurysm of the peroneal artery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>Jeremy</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ferranti</surname><given-names>Katelynn</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Radtka</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FACS</degrees><email>jradtka@pennstatehealth.psu.edu</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>College of Medicine, Pennsylvania State University, Hershey, Pa</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Division of Vascular Surgery, Penn State Heart and Vascular Institute, Pennsylvania State University College of Medicine, Hershey, Pa</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Correspondence: John Radtka, MD, FACS, Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center, 500 University Dr, Mail Code H053, Room C4632, Hershey, PA 17033 <email>jradtka@pennstatehealth.psu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>A mycotic peroneal artery aneurysm (MPAA) is a rare diagnosis. We describe a case of a patient with active fungal endocarditis who developed right lower extremity pain. Imaging demonstrated that this patient had an MPAA. This was treated with open ligation of the peroneal artery, and decompression of the aneurysm sac was performed for symptom relief. Although a rare diagnosis, MPAA should be considered in patients with a history of endocarditis who present with leg pain.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Infected aneurysm</kwd><kwd>Pseudoaneurysm</kwd><kwd>Infrainguinal</kwd><kwd>Endocarditis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Infective endocarditis is caused by a bacterial or fungal infection that damages the endocardium and heart valves. The origin of this infection has many sources, but it is a known complication of intravenous (IV) drug abuse. An accumulation of bacteria and cells, or vegetations, can occur on the valves or the damaged endocardium. These vegetations put the patient at risk for embolic episodes such as strokes. Other complications of infective endocarditis include heart failure, periannular abscess, splenic abscess, pulmonary emboli, and mycotic aneurysms.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p><p id="p0015">Mycotic aneurysms are a known complication of infective endocarditis and occur in roughly 1% to 5% of cases.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> These aneurysms occur owing to embolization of the vasa vasorum secondary to bacterial or fungal elements and this results in an infection of the arterial wall and ultimately arterial wall dilation.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Mycotic aneurysms can be found in any artery of the body, but are most commonly found in the aorta and carotid arteries.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Mycotic peroneal artery aneurysms (MPAAs) are rare and are limited to case reports.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> We present a case of symptomatic MPAA in a patient with fungal endocarditis. The patient provided consent for publication of the images and clinical details in this report.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Case report</title><p id="p0020">A 32-year-old man with a history of IV drug abuse, hepatitis C, and endocarditis underwent mechanical mitral valve replacement (37-mm mechanical St. Jude; Abbott, St Paul, Minn) and tricuspid valve annuloplasty (36-mm Edwards MC3; Edwards Life Sciences, Irvine, Calif) 3&#x000a0;years before this evaluation. After this surgery the patient was maintained on coumadin and he discontinued his IV drug use. The patient was not enrolled in any drug counselling program and he had a relapse of his IV drug use after 1&#x000a0;year of abstinence. During a workup for fevers and night sweats, he was diagnosed with fungal endocarditis and blood cultures positive for <italic>Candida parapsilosis</italic>. A transesophageal echocardiogram demonstrated a 1.2-&#x000a0;&#x000d7; 0.6-cm vegetation on the mechanical mitral valve. The patient was prescribed IV caspofungin and a redo mechanical mitral valve replacement was planned. During a preoperative evaluation, the patient complained of a 2-month history of persistent right calf pain. A computed tomography scan with contrast of the right lower extremity demonstrated a 2.7-&#x000a0;&#x000d7; 3.2-&#x000a0;&#x000d7; 3.2-cm saccular aneurysm of his right peroneal artery just distal to the tibioperoneal trunk (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig&#x000a0;1</xref>). For this reason, the patient was referred to the vascular surgery clinic.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Computed tomography scan of the right peroneal artery aneurysm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0025">Upon evaluation, the patient denied symptoms of classic claudication but stated that it hurt when walking and had caused him to limp. The patient's right calf was slightly larger than the left; however, it was tender to palpation. He had a palpable right posterior tibial and dorsalis pedis pulse. A right lower extremity arterial duplex confirmed the MPAA (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig&#x000a0;2</xref>) and that there was inline blood flow to the foot through the other tibial arteries. In the setting of the patient's fungal endocarditis, a diagnosis of a mycotic aneurysm was made. Owing to the compressive symptoms that the patient was experiencing, he was consented for open ligation of the peroneal artery with decompression of the aneurysm sac. Exposure was obtained through a medial approach and a tourniquet was used for proximal control. The peroneal artery was ligated proximally and distally to the aneurysm. The aneurysm was then decompressed. Cultures of the evacuated hematoma and of the aneurysm wall were negative. A completion angiogram confirmed continued perfusion to the foot through the anterior and posterior tibial arteries (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig&#x000a0;3</xref>). The&#x000a0;remainder of his postoperative course was uneventful, and he was discharged home on postoperative day&#x000a0;3.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p><bold>A,</bold> Longitudinal view demonstrates flow into aneurysm. <bold>B,</bold> Transverse view demonstrates aneurysm size (2.5&#x000a0;&#x000d7; 3.91&#x000a0;cm). The <italic>arrow</italic> demonstrates the peroneal artery.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Fig&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Angiogram of the lower extremity after ligation of the peroneal artery demonstrates patent posterior tibial and anterior tibial arteries.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0030">An MPAA is a rare diagnosis. To our knowledge, there have only been five prior reports of this diagnosis. Four of these patients presented in a similar manner as our patient, with calf pain.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Previous reports of this type of aneurysm have been associated with bacterial endocarditis, specifically <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, <italic>Streptococcus mitis groups</italic>, and Acinetobcter.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> This patient had culture proven <italic>C parapsilosis</italic> endocarditis and was receiving IV antifungals at the time of aneurysm diagnosis. The intraoperative cultures of the hematoma and of the aneurysm wall were negative; however, up to 25% of mycotic aneurysms can be culture negative.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Even though the patient had a previous episode of endocarditis, he did not develop symptoms until after his most recent episode was diagnosed. For this reason, we believe that this patient's MPAA was a result of his most recent episode of infectious endocarditis rather than a consequence of a previous episode.</p><p id="p0035">In this case, the MPAA was diagnosed using both computed tomography and arterial duplex ultrasound scanning. He did not undergo screening for concomitant fungal mycotic aneurysms because the incidence of concomitant fungal mycotic aneurysms is not known and the number of mycotic aneurysms secondary to fungal endocarditis is small.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Mycotic aneurysms secondary to bacterial endocarditis have been studied more extensively secondary to its higher prevalence. Multiple mycotic aneurysms were found in 23% of patients with bacterial endocarditis; however, this report was before the use of antibiotics and valve replacement surgery.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Antibiotic therapy has dramatically decreased the incidence of mycotic aneurysms.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> At this time, there are no recommendations on surveillance imaging of other arterial trees in patients with a single mycotic aneurysm. Surveillance imaging would be difficult because mycotic aneurysms can occur in any vascular bed and the imaging would have to be extensive.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref></p><p id="p0040">The experience with treatment of aneurysms in this location has been limited; however, multiple different techniques have proven to be successful. Open surgical procedures such as arterial ligation, primary repair of the artery, and vein bypass have been performed.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> These aneurysms have also been treated by endovascular methods. Both thrombin injection through a balloon catheter and coil embolization in combination with a covered stent has been used.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> We opted to perform an open repair secondary to the compressive symptoms that the patient was experiencing. Open exploration allows for decompression of compartment syndrome and allows for debridement of any devitalized muscle. The use of the tourniquet at the level of the thigh also allowed for arterial control. This method could potentially decrease the chance of blood loss from dissection proximal and distal to the aneurysm. Ligation of the peroneal artery was selected because the patient was known to have a patent ipsilateral anterior and posterior tibial artery from preoperative imaging. The approach that we described also does not require prosthetic material to remain in situ, which could be a source of future infection.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0045">An MPAA is a rare diagnosis. Open ligation and aneurysm sac decompression in patients with adequate collateral circulation is an ideal treatment for those with compressive symptoms from a mycotic peroneal artery aneurysm.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mocchegiani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications of infective endocarditis</article-title><source>Caridovasc Hematol Disord Drug Targets</source><volume>9</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>248</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baddour</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>V.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tleyieh</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rybak</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infective endocarditis in adults: diagnosis, antimicrobial therapy, and management of complications: a scientific statement for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association</article-title><source>Circulation</source><volume>132</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1435</fpage><lpage>1486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26373316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albayrak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saglam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmiler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Degirmenci</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large mycotic aneurysm of the peroneal artery</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Clin Ultrasound</source><volume>35</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17354242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elford</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roobottom</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycotic pseudoaneurysm of the common peroneal artery treated with direct human thrombin injection</article-title><source>Clin Radiol Extra</source><volume>57</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycotic aneurysms of the tibioperoneal arteries</article-title><source>Ann Vasc Surg</source><volume>13</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10072460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shyam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Unnikrishnan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudhindran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ruptured mycotic aneurysm of the peroneal artery</article-title><source>EJVES Extra</source><volume>10</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonatto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Viazzo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robaldo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endovascular treatment of a symptomatic mycotic aneurysm of the peroneal artery</article-title><source>Ann Vasc Surg</source><volume>25</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>982.e11</fpage><lpage>982.e14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busuttil</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machleder</surname><given-names>H.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>W.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteriological and surgical determinants of survival in patients with mycotic aneurysms</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Vasc Surg</source><volume>1</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6436514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Wagenen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Passaro</surname><given-names>E.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Arterial infection</article-title><source>Curr Probl Surg</source><volume>115</volume><year>1975</year><fpage>5</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stengel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolferth</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycotic (bacterial) aneurysms of intravascular origin</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><volume>31</volume><year>1923</year><fpage>527</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ledochowski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friggeri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;rare case of Streptococcus agalactiae mycotic aneurysm and review of the literature</article-title><source>Infection</source><volume>42</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24390817</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="d31e44"><p id="ntpara0010">Author conflict of interest: none.</p></fn><fn id="d31e47"><p id="ntpara0015">The editors and reviewers of this article have no relevant financial relationships to disclose per the Journal policy that requires reviewers to decline review of any manuscript for which they may have a conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>