<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Urol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Urol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Urology Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2214-4420</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34026556</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8120933</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2214-4420(21)00141-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eucr.2021.101701</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101701</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Inflammation and Infection</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reno-appendiceal fistula in autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Madison S.</given-names></name><email>madison.hill@som.umaryland.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Villela</surname><given-names>Natalia Arias</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>LaMattina</surname><given-names>John C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Rasko</surname><given-names>Yvonne M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>Michael W.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Urology, University of Maryland School of Medicine, 655 W. Baltimore Street, Baltimore MD 21201, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Surgery, Division of Transplant Surgery, University of Maryland School of Medicine, 655 W. Baltimore Street, Baltimore MD 21201, USA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Surgery, Division of Plastic Surgery, University of Maryland School of Medicine, 655 W. Baltimore Street, Baltimore MD 21201, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. 419 West Redwood Street Baltimore, MD 21201 USA. <email>madison.hill@som.umaryland.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>38</volume><elocation-id>101701</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>We present a very rare Case of a 53-year-old female with autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD) who was incidentally found to have a reno-appendiceal fistula while undergoing open bilateral nephrectomy. The mid-portion of the appendix was fistulized to a cyst in the lower pole of the right kidney. The etiology was likely due to chronic inflammation. An appendectomy was performed along with the planned right nephrectomy to ensure complete removal of the fistulous tract.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0015"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0010">The development of a fistulous communication between the kidney and intestinal tract is a rare event.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">These fistulas are usually a consequence of chronic, inflammatory disease of the urinary or gastrointestinal tract.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">There has never been a report of a reno-appendiceal fistula in a patient with ADPKD.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</kwd><kwd>Fistula</kwd><kwd>Appendix</kwd><kwd>Reno-alimentary fistula</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group id="kwrds0015"><title>Abbreviations</title><kwd>ADPK, Dautosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</kwd><kwd>UTI, urinary tract infection</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0025">The development of a fistulous communication between the kidney and intestinal tract is a rare event that has been cited in the literature a little over 100 times with the ascending and descending colon being most commonly implicated. The etiology may be secondary to trauma, iatrogenic, or spontaneous due to underlying renal or intestinal tract pathology.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> To the best of the authors&#x02019; knowledge, there has never been a report of a reno-appendiceal fistula in a patient with ADPKD. We present a Case of a patient with ADPKD incidentally diagnosed with a reno-appendiceal fistula while undergoing an open bilateral nephrectomy.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="p0030">A 53-year-old female with a past medical history of ADPKD, on hemodialysis for 10 years, presented for a scheduled open bilateral nephrectomy, cholecystectomy, and ventral hernia repair. She had previous abdominal surgery for diverticular disease, including colostomy creation and take-down, which was complicated by a ventral hernia. The patient also had a history of an infected left renal cyst requiring drainage by interventional radiology, but no history of procedures on the right kidney. She was, however, evaluated in the emergency room two years prior to presentation for right-sided abdominal pain and fever, and was found to have an infected cyst in the lower pole of the right kidney. Imaging at that time showed inflammatory fat stranding anterior to the right kidney. She was treated with antibiotics and the infection resolved.</p><p id="p0035">Pre-operative evaluation with a computed tomography (CT) scan of the abdomen and pelvis with intravenous contrast showed large bilateral polycystic kidneys, intrahepatic biliary ductal dilation, and a normal-appearing appendix that was adjacent to the lower pole of the right kidney (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Contrast enhancement was limited by the patient's end stage renal disease and a fistulous tract could not be appreciated. At the time of presentation, the patient was afebrile and hemodynamically stable, without leukocytosis. She did not report any abdominal pain and had no history of lower urinary tract symptoms or recurrent urinary tract infections (UTIs).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Coronal CT showing appendix sweeping adjacent to a right sided renal cyst.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0040">After informed consent was obtained, the patient was taken to the operating room. During the procedure, a large intestinal phlegmon was found adhered to the lower pole of the right kidney. With further dissection of the cecum, it became evident that the mid-portion of the appendix had fistulized to one of the renal cysts. An appendectomy was performed to allow for complete removal of the fistulous tract along with the right kidney (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). The remainder of the surgery was uneventful and there were no significant complications.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Gross image of appendix adhered to right kidney.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Gross image of appendix adhered to right lower pole renal cyst.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="p0045">The surgical pathology report subsequently noted a 9.5 cm in length by 0.9 cm in diameter appendix with a moderately dilated, pink-tan lumen. No gross evidence of acute appendicitis was reported. Firm, fibrous serosal adhesions were noted on both the right kidney and the appendix, but the two organs were separated before reaching pathology in order to be placed into individual specimen containers so no comment on a fistulous tract could be made. A peri-appendiceal organized hematoma was noted on the gross specimen, that the pathologist stated was most likely due to shearing of the blood vessels in the fibrous adhesions between the right kidney and appendix, leading to local hemorrhage and a subsequent inflammatory reaction.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0050">We presented a rare Case of a reno-appendiceal fistula in a patient with ADPKD discovered during open bilateral nephrectomy. Reno-alimentary fistulas are usually a consequence of chronic, inflammatory disease of the urinary or gastrointestinal tract, but can also be due to trauma or iatrogenic. Traditionally, most cases of reno-alimentary fistulas originated from renal disease, particularly xanthogranulomatous pyelonephritis.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> With the advent of minimally invasive surgery, there has been a rise in cases of reno-alimentary fistula development following percutaneous nephrolithotomy.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> The most common locations of reno-alimentary fistulas are reno-colic, which make up about 60% of the reported cases, followed by reno-duodenal, with reno-jejunal and reno-ileal connections being exceedingly rare.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Medical management alone is rarely successful and operative intervention is almost always required.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></p><p id="p0055">Most patients with a reno-alimentary fistula present with renal or gastrointestinal complaints such as flank or abdominal pain, fever, nausea and vomiting, and voiding symptoms like recurrent UTIs, hematuria, pneumaturia, and/or fecaluria.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> While our patient did not present with any of these symptoms, surgical exploration showed a visible connection between the appendix and a right lower pole renal cyst. Lack of urinary symptoms can also be explained by the patients long-standing hemodialysis history, leading to minimal urine production. It is possible that the patient was asymptomatic because the fistulous tract between the two organs had yet to become fully patent, although, a lumen was observed intraoperatively. It is also possible that the renal cyst had successfully contained the contents of the fistulous tract and prevented seeding of gastrointestinal organisms into the kidney. Given the patients prior history of an infected right lower pole cyst, this leads the authors to believe that the fistula originated from renal inflammation surrounding that episode.</p><p id="p0060">Moreover, the presence of appendiceal dilation noted on the surgical pathology report opens the possibility that the fistula could have been appendiceal in origin, potentially from a sub-clinical event of appendicitis, as no account of acute appendicitis was noted in the patient's record. It is also possible that the presence the fistula and local inflammatory response surrounding the right kidney subsequently led to the appendiceal dilation. While the exact origin of the fistula is unknown, it can be assumed that chronic inflammation of either or both organ systems contributed to the development of this fistulous tract.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0065">This is a rare Case report of a reno-appendiceal fistula in a patient with ADPKD. The fistulous tract was incidentally discovered during open bilateral nephrectomy and necessitated an appendectomy for complete removal of the tract. The etiology of the fistulous tract was likely secondary to chronic inflammation in the kidney, appendix, or both. To the best of the authors&#x02019; knowledge, this has never been described in the literature.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Funding sources</title><p id="p0070">This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Consent</title><p id="p0075">Obtained.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Author statement</title><p id="p0080">Madison Hill: Writing &#x02013; original draft, Visualization, Project Administration, Formal Analysis. Natalia Arias Villela: Writing &#x02013; Reviewing and Editing. John LaMattina: Investigation, Resources. Yvonne Rasko: Conceptualization, Investigation. Michael Phelan: Supervision, Project Administration, Conceptualization, Methodology.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0085">None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhaskar</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purkait</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Renal fistulae: different aetiologies, similar management</article-title><source>BMJ Case Rep</source><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bcr-2017-219678</pub-id><comment>Published online</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LeRoy</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colon perforation following percutaneous nephrostomy and renal calculus removal</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1985</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiology.155.1.3975424</pub-id><comment>Published online</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bissada</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reno alimentary fistula: an unusual urological problem</article-title><source><italic>J Urol</italic>. Published online</source><year>1973</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5347(17)60184-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref4">Lin W, Watts K, Aboumohamed A. Renoalimentary fistula: Case report of a renoduodenal fistula and systematic literature review. Urol Case Reports. Published online 2018. doi:10.1016/j.eucr.2018.02.022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardikar</surname><given-names>D.J.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reno alimentary fistulae</article-title><source>IOSR J Dent Med Sci</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9790/0853-13427779</pub-id><comment>Published online</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0090">None.</p></ack></back></article>