<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vasc Surg Cases Innov Tech</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Vasc Surg Cases Innov Tech</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Vascular Surgery Cases and Innovative Techniques</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2468-4287</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32715172</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7371717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2468-4287(20)30074-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvscit.2020.05.009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Endovascular abdominal aortic aneurysm repair in a centenarian</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Bellamkonda</surname><given-names>Kirthi S.</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Tanner</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>Ronnie</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Dardik</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Nassiri</surname><given-names>Naiem</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>naiem.nassiri@yale.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of Vascular and Endovascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, Conn</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Surgery, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, Conn</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Correspondence: Naiem Nassiri, MD, Division of Vascular and Endovascular Surgery, Department of Surgery, Yale University, School of Medicine, 333 Cedar St, New Haven, CT 06510 <email>naiem.nassiri@yale.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>As the general population ages, there will be an increasing number of vascular patients in their 90s and older. However, geriatric patients have historically been turned down for abdominal aortic aneurysm repair despite high aneurysm-related mortality in the unrepaired. Herein, we describe the perioperative considerations and the successful, uncomplicated operative course of a 100-year-old woman who underwent an elective endovascular aortic aneurysm repair for an expanding 5.3-cm abdominal aortic aneurysm. Given a suitable patient, there is acceptable risk profile of an endovascular approach, even in centenarians.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>EVAR</kwd><kwd>Geriatric</kwd><kwd>Centenarian</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Although geriatric patients have historically been turned down for abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA) repair, studies have demonstrated acceptable risk profile of an endovascular approach&#x02014;even in nonagenarians&#x02014;given a suitable patient (&#x0003c;5 comorbidities such as history of cancer, myocardial infarction, hypertension, etc).<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Conversely, patients turned down for AAA repair suffer 83% mortality over 3&#x000a0;years.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> It has thus been concluded that age alone is not an appropriate reason to forego AAA repair.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p id="p0015">To date and to the best of our knowledge, the oldest described elective open AAA repair in the literature has been in a 101-year-old patient.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> However, current literature has scant evidence of centenarians undergoing endovascular aortic aneurysm repair (EVAR). We describe important ethical considerations around shared decision-making, and the successful operative course of a 100-year-old woman who underwent elective EVAR for an expanding 5.3-cm AAA.</p><p id="p0020">Consent was obtained to publish this case.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Case report</title><p id="p0025">A 100-year-old woman presented for a second opinion for an expanding infrarenal AAA. Cardiovascular history included controlled hypertension, stable coronary artery disease (ejection fraction of 75%, no prior interventions), and stable hyperlipidemia. Medical history was, otherwise, notable for a history of resolved immune thrombocytopenic purpura, glaucoma, and hypothyroidism. On physical examination, she was a healthy appearing female patient who seemed to be younger than her stated age, was well-nourished, and in no acute distress. She had a body mass index of 21.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. We palpated a nontender, pulsatile, midline abdominal mass with diminished but palpable femoral pulses bilaterally.</p><p id="p0030">Computed tomography angiography demonstrated a 5.3-cm infrarenal bilobed AAA with focal outpouchings and ulcerated plaques. The aneurysm had grown from 4.9&#x000a0;cm 6&#x000a0;months prior, as measured side-by-side by the treating vascular surgeon. The proximal neck had a length of 1.5&#x000a0;cm and a diameter of 1.8&#x000a0;cm. There was moderate calcification throughout her aortoiliac vessels extending into her femoral arteries. The left and right common iliac arteries were 8.6 and 8.8&#x000a0;mm, respectively (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig&#x000a0;1</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Preoperative computed tomography scan reconstruction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0035">A geriatric evaluation was completed. Medication review showed she took 81&#x000a0;mg of aspirin, diltiazem, rosuvastatin, and ezetimibe. Mild cognitive impairment was noted on the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MOCA of 23/30), with perfect executive function. She had good mood and functional status. Preoperative cardiac risk evaluation revealed no ischemic changes. Preoperative creatinine was 0.89.</p><p id="p0040">A majority of consultation time over two sessions with the patient and her family before and after geriatric conversation were dedicated to shared decision making around goals of care. The patient was adamant that she receive the best care for this life-threatening condition and was seeking a second opinion after being previously refused operative treatment. She was informed of the rupture and mortality risk, but given her age, additional discussions were also critical. Her baseline functional status was excellent. She lived alone, used no assistive walking devices, and was able to perform normal and instrumental activities of daily living. The risk discussion included loss of independence from possible loss of limb and other complications. In addition, code status and advance directive conversation occurred with patient and family. The patient chose to remain full code, including cardiopulmonary resuscitation and intubation, after risks and outcomes were discussed.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Surgical technique</title><p id="p0045">She was admitted to the hospital the day before surgery for preoperative intravenous hydration and contrast allergy prophylaxis. Intraoperative flush abdominal aortography confirmed computed tomography angiography findings and a suitable anatomy for the proposed repair (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig&#x000a0;2</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Preoperative aortography demonstrating anatomy consistent with the computed tomography scan.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0050">EVAR was performed uneventfully under general anesthesia via femoral cutdown with standard technique. A Medtronic Endurant II (Medtronic, Minneapolis, Minn) modular bifurcated device measuring 23&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;13&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;166&#x000a0;mm and left iliac limb measuring 16&#x000a0;mm &#x000d7; 10 mm&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;93&#x000a0;mm were deployed, and kissing balloon angioplasty of the deployed limbs performed (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig&#x000a0;3</xref>). Postoperative angiography demonstrated successful repair without endoleaks (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig&#x000a0;4</xref>). A left common femoral endarterectomy was performed upon completion of the case. Her postoperative course was unremarkable. She was discharged on postoperative day 4, to allow adequate independant ambulation before discharge, and to make arrangements for short-term rehabilitation.<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Kissing balloon angioplasty of iliac crossing sections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Fig&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Postoperative angiogram demonstrating absence of endoleak.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p><p id="p0055">She was seen at 2&#x000a0;weeks and 6&#x000a0;months for follow-up. All incisions had healed. She had no abdominal or back complaints and her lower extremities were well-perfused. Serial imaging revealed a stable aneurysm sac with no evidence of endoleak. She remained highly functional and was living independently at the time of last follow-up.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0060">In 2015, the world's population of centenarians was nearly 500,000. In 2050, that number is predicted to be more than 3,000,000.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> As the general population ages, there will be an increasing number of vascular patients aged 90s and older.</p><p id="p0065">Centenarians with AAA pose a number of special ethical and operative considerations. The 1-year actuarial mortality of a 100-year-old woman is 30% with expected lifespan of 2.42&#x000a0;years, and the probability of a 5.3-cm AAA rupturing within 1&#x000a0;year is 9.4% and within 2&#x000a0;years is approximately 20%,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> We highlight here that, in well-selected patients, the risk of intervention may align with goals defined in shared decision making between patients, family members, surgeons, and geriatricians.</p><p id="p0070">Lath et&#x000a0;al<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> note considerations in evaluating suitability of the very old for elective repair: &#x0201c;aneurysm size, symptomatic nature of disease, history of elderly family members and overall general good condition.&#x0201d; Geriatric evaluation includes assessment of cognition, functional status, mood, support system, and overall medical state, addressing Lath et&#x000a0;al's point about &#x0201c;overall condition.&#x0201d;</p><p id="p0075">Aneurysms exhibiting rapid expansion, saccular and/or ulcerative features, and those in patients with low body surface area are at higher than average risk for rupture. Our patient was a small framed woman&#x02014;5&#x02019;0&#x0201d;, 37% body surface area index suggesting a higher than average rupture risk.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> She had a 4-mm expansion over 6 months indicating a near-rapid growth.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Although the natural history of saccular aneurysms is poorly defined, general consensus does suggest a relatively lower threshold for elective repair compared with fusiform aneurysms.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Given the morphology and progression of this patient's AAA, it is safe to assume a greater than average annual rupture risk for this size group, which we estimate between 10% and 20%.</p><p id="p0080">Although the frailty score was not prospectively calculated, information from geriatric evaluation indicates Edmonton score of 1 of 17 (no frailty).<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> A study of centenarian survival shows that 1-year mortality is a mere 12.5% for an individual performing instrumental activities of daily living unassisted.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Accounting for mild cognitive impairment and no frailty, 1-year mortality is 15%.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Based on the age-adjusted estimated glomerular filtration rate, the 2-year mortality is less than 15%.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref></p><p id="p0085">Given the increased risk of rupture and less than 15% risk of all-cause mortality per year in this patient, she is an operative candidate. Perioperative risk was considered. Delirium is a concern in the elderly; evidence suggests increased risk only in MOCA of less than 15; this patient has MOCA of 23.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Age of more than 70&#x000a0;years correlates with only a small increase in major perioperative complications (7.5% vs 4.8%).<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> The EUROSTAR study demonstrated that EVAR patients return to preoperative status sooner.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> In the 80- to 99-year-old age group, multiple studies have shown EVAR is safe and effective with acceptable risk profile. Judicious patient selection remains crucial.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p><p id="p0090">This patient had previously been refused intervention based on age alone, and was adamant that full consideration be given to her case. She was seeking a second opinion, and fully engaged in decision making, involving her children. In these cases, discussions about the goals of care must go beyond rupture and mortality risks alone; we dedicated multiple consultations to discussions surrounding major morbidities and the resulting impact on independence, and ensured that the patient and family considered code status and advance directives.</p><p id="p0095">EVAR is a safe treatment option for appropriately selected centenarians with need for elective AAA repair; geriatric evaluation and shared decision making are critical additions to the consultation process.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sicard</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curci</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geraghty</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acceptable risk but small benefit of endovascular aneurysm repair in nonagenarians</article-title><source>Ann Vasc Surg</source><volume>24</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20036490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezayat</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sambol</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Endovascular aneurysm repair in nonagenarians is safe and effective</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Vasc Surg</source><volume>52</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1140</fpage><lpage>1146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21050985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>I.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognosis of patients turned down for conventional abdominal aortic aneurysm repair in the endovascular and sonographic era: Szilagyi revisited?</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Vasc Surg</source><volume>33</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11296328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wheatley</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorsuch</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuff</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular procedures in nonagenarians and centenarians are safe</article-title><source>Am J Surg</source><volume>201</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21367367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lath</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alshafie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Open repair of abdominal aortic aneurysm in a centenarian</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Vasc Surg</source><volume>53</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20864297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shafei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Attar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ebrahim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ruptured large abdominal aortic aneurysm in a centenarian: a case report with a favorable outcome</article-title><source>Vasc Surg</source><volume>28</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>440</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with subjective life expectancy: comparison with actuarial life expectancy</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Prev Med Public Health</source><volume>50</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>240</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28768402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lederle</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Blebea</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rupture rate of large abdominal aortic aneurysms in patients refusing or unfit for elective repair</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>287</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>2968</fpage><lpage>2972</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fillinger</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matyal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdan</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relative importance of aneurysm diameter and body size for predicting AAA rupture in men and women</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Vasc Surg</source><volume>57</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>288</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hallin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergqvist</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Literature review of surgical management of abdominal aortic aneurysm</article-title><source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><volume>22</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11506510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boonn</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lys-Dobradin</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairman</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>E.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;modern experience with saccular aortic aneurysms</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Vasc Surg</source><volume>57</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23127980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaikof</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalman</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eskandari</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Society for Vascular Surgery practice guidelines on the care of patients with an abdominal aortic aneurysm</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><volume>67</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29268916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rolfson</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuyuki</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahir</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockwood</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validity and reliability of the Edmonton Frail Scale</article-title><source>Age Ageing</source><volume>35</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16757522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mossakowska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broczek</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieczorowska-Tobis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klich-R&#x00105;czka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pawlik-Pachucka</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive performance and functional status are the major factors predicting survival of centenarians in Poland</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Geron A Biol Sci Med Sci</source><volume>69</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1275</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frailty and cognitive impairment in predicting mortality among oldest-old people</article-title><source>Front Agin Neurosci</source><volume>10</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>295</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandelli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riva</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tettamanti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Detoma</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacomin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucca</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality prediction in the oldest old with five different equations to estimate glomerular filtration rate: the health and anemia population-based study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>10</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>e0136039</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26317988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Styra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimas</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baston</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elgie-Watson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flockhart</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of preoperative cognitive impairment and type of vascular surgery procedure on postoperative delirium with associated cost implications</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Vasc Surg</source><volume>69</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29941317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Png</surname><given-names>C.Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadros</surname><given-names>R.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faries</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lookstein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of age on post-EVAR outcomes</article-title><source>Ann Vasc Surg</source><volume>35</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27236092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leurs</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myhre</surname><given-names>H.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endovascular repair of abdominal aortic aneurysm in octogenarians: an analysis based on EUROSTAR data</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Vasc Surg</source><volume>42</volume><year>2005</year><comment>624.e1-624.e9</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minor</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellozy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroccio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endovascular aortic aneurysm repair in the octogenarian: is it worthwhile?</article-title><source>Arch Surg</source><volume>139</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15006890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsilimparis</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricotta</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names><suffix>II</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Age-stratified results from 20,095 aortoiliac aneurysm repairs: should we approach octogenarians and nonagenarians differently?</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Am Coll Surg</source><volume>215</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>690</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22863795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdulrahman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prendergast</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ongu'ti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abdominal aortic aneurysm repair in nonagenarians</article-title><source>Ann Vasc Surg</source><volume>29</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25461753</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="d32e43"><p id="ntpara0010">Author conflict of interest: N.N. is a consultant and surgical proctor for Medtronic Aortic, Inc.</p></fn><fn id="d32e46"><p id="ntpara0015">The editors and reviewers of this article have no relevant financial relationships to disclose per the Journal policy that requires reviewers to decline review of any manuscript for which they may have a conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>